Welcome to unit 7, y'all. And we're
going to start by talking about the
debates that led the United States to
get its big boy imperialism pants on.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay. Now,
before we jump straight into the debates
over American imperialism, let me start
with a definition and some context.
Okay. So, imperialism by definition
describes a process by which a powerful
state extends authority over another
weaker state in order to exploit its
resources. And that authority can come
in a variety of flavors like economic
control or direct political control etc.
But whatever the flavor, the ultimate
outcome is a loss of sovereignty and
self-determination for the colonized.
And don't forget that this fair country
that we've been studying throughout the
whole course started as an imperial
venture visa v Big Mama Britain. And
further recall that Americans in those
days fought Big Mama off precisely
because they believed through and
through, up and down, left and right,
inward and outward, that imperial
empires were unjust and primarily
exploitative. But it only took a little
over a hundred years for American policy
makers to be like, well, you know, we
were young and stupid back then, so
let's get this imperial party started.
So, how, my dear people, did Americans
go from fighting and dying for freedom
from an imperial state to becoming an
imperial state of its own? Well, that's
a fine question, and I'm about to him
explain it up real nice for you. But
first, let me mention that if you need
help getting an A in your class and a
five on your exam in May, then you might
want to check out my A Push Heimler
review guide. It's got exclusive videos,
note guides to follow along, practice
questions, practice exams, etc. It is
the fastest way to study and if that's
something that you're into, the link is
in the description. Okay, so now let me
answer the question of how the United
States got to the point where claiming
an imperial empire seemed like a
reasonable choice. So in the last
period, we saw how foreign policy makers
and wealthy industrialists began to look
outside the borders of the United States
in order to secure new markets for
American goods and expanded access to
raw material. And this was going on at
the very same time that European states
were developing vast sea-based empires
and colonizing the whole dang world. And
the US was late to the overseas
expansion party mainly because the civil
war and reconstruction claimed a lot of
attention in the 19th century. But with
the rapid expansion of industrialization
and the growing wealth of the United
States at the end of the 19th century,
the country was now ready to join the
rest of the imperial European powers to
build an overseas empire. And that's
just the immediate context. Like if you
go back further, US policy has always
favored imperial expansion in one way or
another. Just ask the many groups of
indigenous Americans who lost their land
to westward expansion or ask the
Mexicans who lost a third of their
territory after the Mexican-American
War. I could go on. And so now that
we're crossing into the 20th century and
America stands poised to expand
overseas, it is not a surprising
development because, you know, manifest
destiny has just always been our thing.
Okay. So, as it became abundantly clear
that a growing impulse for overseas
expansion was driving the US toward
empire building, it sparked a fierce
debate about whether it was proper for
the US to play the role of an imperial
power in the world. And there were two
sides to that debate. And first, I'll
introduce you to the imperialists.
They're the Americans who favored
overseas expansion because they believed
America was destined to expand their
culture and institutions to peoples
around the world. And they had four
reasons to support that claim. First,
they argued that America ought to expand
overseas to take advantage of economic
opportunities. And the truth is, in
almost every case of imperial expansion,
the most powerful rationale is always
the boom boom. Anyway, much of the
economic rationale for overseas
expansion was rooted in the foreign
policy of Secretary of State William
Seward, who served under Abraham Lincoln
and then Andrew Johnson. So Seward
believed that the key to accessing the
great wealth bound up in Asian markets
was to acquire a snowy frozen piece of
Russian territory, namely Alaska. And so
in 1868, Seward negotiated the purchase
of Alaska from Russia. And because many
Americans didn't see the point of owning
a massive piece of frozen territory that
wasn't even connected to the mainland of
the United States, the purchase became
known as Seward's Folly. Man, that
Seward is such an idiot.
>> I know. Seward, more like Sue Turd, am I
right? However, it turned out that
Seward was just ahead of his time
because by the last decade of the 19th
century, the panic of 1893 had created
severe economic distress for many
Americans. And so, foreign policy makers
decided that the solution to improve the
economy in the homeland was to open new
markets in Asia in order to sell
American goods. And at that point,
Alaska became a critical asset for
gaining access to those markets. And
Seward was all
okay. Second, the imperialist argued
that America ought to expand overseas
because of their belief in various
racial theories. For example, the
growing acceptance of the ideas of
social Darwinism encouraged the pursuit
of overseas empires. And I shall explain
why presently. So recall from the last
unit that Charles Darwin argued that in
nature only the strongest species
survive precisely because they are the
best adapted to the changing
environment. And then further recall
that social Darwinists applied the same
logic to social realities in order to
explain why some Americans were wealthy
and other Americans were poor. namely
that the rich were those who had best
adapted to the new industrial
environment and the poor were those who
had not. In other words, to say it real
plain, if you were rich and powerful,
that was the sign that you were best
adapted to the new social and economic
environment. And then it's not much of a
journey from there to looking at the
whole dane country and concluding that
since industrialization had made it
wealthy and powerful, it must mean that
America had become among the fittest to
survive. Furthermore, this ideology
stoked the flames of American
exceptionalism, which was an idea that
the United States as a nation blessed
above all other nations with liberty and
a flourishing civilization. And
therefore, in the context of debates
about imperialism, some Americans
believed that it was the duty of
Americans to spread these blessings to
those lesser people throughout the
world. And probably the most famous
American articulation of this idea came
from Minister Josiah Strong. And he
argued that the Anglo-Saxon race,
particularly the American flavor of that
race, was the absolute apex of human
evolution. And as a minister, Strong
added that it was the Christian duty of
Americans to acquire a worldwide empire
so that they could spread Christianity
and the glories of Western civilization
to those backward and dark people
groups. And as it turned out, that idea
was indeed a steaming pile of Christian
duty. Anyway, the proper name for this
impulse was known as the civilizing
mission. The principles of which were
most famously articulated in Rard
Kipling's poem, The White Man's Burden.
Okay. The third argument for overseas
expansion concerned American competition
with European empire. You see,
throughout the 19th century, Western
European states have been expanding
their sea-based empires rapidly,
especially in Asia and Africa. And
because the global balance of power was
now decided by which state held the
biggest empire, policymakers in the
United States feared that if they did
not begin a project of overseas
expansion, then they could never compete
with other European superpowers. And
that would just be a bummer, you know.
But anyway, in 1890, a US naval officer
named Alfred the Mahan provided a clear
solution for this fear, namely an
expanded US Navy. Now, his book was
called the influence of sea power upon
history. And in it, he argued that all
the most powerful states in the world
had one thing in common, namely, they
had a navy powerful enough to make other
states poop their pants. Therefore, the
key to projecting power in such a world
was to invest heavily in naval power.
And so, by 1886, the federal government
had appropriated funds for two
state-of-the-art steel hold naval ships.
And by the end of the century, they had
built three more. And then finally, the
fourth argument for overseas expansion
was the closing of the Western Frontier.
So in 1890, the census revealed a
shocking demographic truth, namely that
the American western frontier had at
last been settled. In other words, the
western frontier was gone. And this was
a big deal because since the earliest
days of the American experiment, the
western frontier played a critical role
in America's social and cultural
development. And now that the frontier
was closed, all that potential
opportunity was closed as well. And to
many people, that felt like an
existential threat to life in America.
But don't worry, because here comes a
historian Frederick Jackson Turner, who
published what became known as his
frontier thesis, arguing that it was
simply not an option for Americans to
lack a frontier in which to expand. In
fact, the disappearance of the frontier
was kind of an existential crisis by
Turner's reckoning because expansion was
actually the condition in which American
democracy could exist and thrive. And of
course, that meant that the future of
America depended on adopting a new
frontier, which would come in the form
of overseas expansion. Okay, so we've
heard the arguments for American
imperial expansion. So, now let's hear
from the folks who opposed such a
development, and they were known as the
Anti-Imperialists. So, in 1898, they
formed the Anti-Imperialist League in
response to America's attempt to annex
the Philippines. And I'll tell you about
that in the next video. Anyway, this
group essentially articulated three
reasons why it would be altogether dumb
for the US to pursue an empire. First,
they argued that imperial expansion
would violate the principles of
self-determination for other nations. To
that end, they invoked what they called
the spirit of 1776, arguing that a core
principle of the founding of the United
States was that each nation ought to
have the right to govern themselves. And
therefore, to rule another nation across
the sea as a colony would violate the
American commitment to the principle of
government by the consent of the
government. In other words, that's kind
of like our whole thing. So, let's not
dump on other people's
self-determination. Okay. Second,
anti-imperialists evoke the long
American tradition of isolationism with
respect to world affairs. You may recall
that this was a principle that stretched
all the way back to George Washington's
farewell address in which he warned that
getting involved in entangling foreign
alliances would only drag the US into
conflicts in which it had no business
participating. And that isolationism
also connects to the Monroe Doctrine
since it mandated that Europeans stay
out of America's business and America
will stay out of Europe's business. And
then third, the anti-imperialists also
made use of racial theories to support
their side. And poundfor-pound, the
anti-imperialists actually leaned on
these kind of arguments more than the
imperialist. For example, Andrew
Carnegie, one of the most famous
anti-imperialists, wrote an essay in
1898 called Distant Possessions. And in
it, he argued that by annexing the
Philippines or any other overseas
territory, millions of non-white people
will be added to the American
population. And he warned that in places
like the Philippines, it would be quote
impossible for our own race to be
produced and therefore the expansion of
American empire should be opposed in
order to uphold the superiority of the
Anglo-Saxon race. And ultimately, as
we'll discover in the next video, the
imperialists won the debate. And after
the American victory in the
SpanishAmerican War, the United States
got its big boy imperial pants all the
way on and started a proper overseas
empire. Well, okay. You can click here
to watch my other videos for unit 7, or
you can click here to grab my A Push
Himler review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm lur
out.